Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin

Zürich, Switzerland ibo.mohsin@gmail.com

Last Updated: April, 2022

https://ibomohsin.github.io/ linkedin.com/in/ibrahimalabdulmohsin/

I am a research scientist at Google Brain, developing tools for understanding deep learning and improving its societal impact, particularly relating to fairness. Previously, I founded and led the Advanced Analytics team at Saudi Aramco, managed the company's Enterprise Analytics program, and was a technical lead at its digital transformation program.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy	DhD	Computer Science	VALICT	CDA. 4 0 / 4 0
DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY	- PNI).	Computer Science	KAUSI	(₁ PA·4()/4()

Thesis title: "Learning via Query Synthesis." Committee: X. Zhang, X. Gao, D. Keyes (KAUST), and W. Wang (UCLA). 2012 — 2017

Master of Science, Electrical Engineering, Stanford University, GPA: 4.15 / 4.0

Emphasis on networked systems, artificial intelligence, and operations management. 2009-2011

Bachelor of Science, Computer Engineering, University of Nebraska, Lincoln, GPA: 3.98 / 4.0

Highest Distinction, Minor in Economics. 2000 — 2005

SKILLS

Research & Development Authored 1 book, +25 research papers, 1 granted patent and 3 pending patents.

Communication English (fluent), Arabic (native), German (elementary, A1).

Technical Data science, artificial intelligence, modeling & optimization, digital transformation, networked systems

(certified by Cisco, Juniper and Alcatel-Lucent).

Leadership +2 years managing corporate-wide enterprise analytics program, leading the advanced analytics team,

and serving as a technical lead at digital transformation program at Saudi Aramco.

SELECTED ACTIVITIES

Program committee member at NeurIPS, ICML, ICLR, AAAI, and IJCAI.	2017 — Present
Reviewer for TMLR, IEEE PAMI, IEEE TNNLS, and IEEE Communications Letters.	2019 — Present
Member of the S20 Task Force (Digital Revolution).	2020
Chair of AI track of the 2019 Arab-American Frontiers Symposium.	2019

AWARDS

2016
2012
2012
2009
2007
2005

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

RESEARCH & DEVELOPMENT SCIENTIST

NOV 2019 — Present

Google, Brain Team

Zürich, Switzerland

- Led / co-led several projects to improve understanding of deep learning and improve ML fairness; e.g. pretraining with random labels, debiasing neural networks and datasets, data scaling laws, and calibration.
- Key member of a moonshot team for machine learning fairness in healthcare.
- Member of the Google Scholarship review team and mentor of AI residents.

LEAD, ADVANCED ANALYTICS

NOV 2017 — OCT 2019

Saudi Aramco, Corporate Applications Dept

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

- Founded and led the Advanced Analytics team that was responsible for developing AI solutions, managing analytics infrastructures, conducting research collaboration with academia, evaluating technologies, and developing roadmaps.
- Technical lead at the Digital Transformation Program, with a mission to accelerate the adoption of artificial intelligence at the company. Sectors include downstream, supply chain, sales & marketing, IT, cybersecurity and HR.

PERFORMANCE ENGINEER

JUN 2011 — AUG 2012

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

- Performance management and capacity planning for enterprise communications services such as the Data Center, the Internet, Extranet, and Wireless LAN infrastructures.
- Developed an analytics tool for automated performance analysis and SLA compliance assessment.

DATA NETWORK ENGINEER

JUL 2005 — AUG 2009

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

Saudi Aramco, Comm. Eng. Department

Saudi Aramco, Comm. Eng. Department

- Key member of an 18-month IT network security project for securing critical facilities.
- Project manager for a 1-year CCTV surveillance camera systems project (involving civil and communications work).
- Design, installation, configuration, reviews, upgrades, and troubleshooting of data networks.